<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The consolations of David, breefly applied to Queene Elizabeth in a sermon preached in Oxford the 17. of Nouember. By Iohn Prime, 1588.</title>
            <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101191</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837013</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837013</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10110)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The consolations of David, breefly applied to Queene Elizabeth in a sermon preached in Oxford the 17. of Nouember. By Iohn Prime, 1588.</title>
                  <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold [by T. Cooke] in Paules Church-yeard, at the signe of the Tygres head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:1"/>
            <p>THE CONSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATIONS OF DAVID, BREEFLY APPLIED TO QVEENE ELIZABETH: IN A Sermon preached in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the 17. of Nouember.</p>
            <p>By IOHN PRIME, 1588.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 23. ver. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is my Sheepheard, I ſhall not want.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ IMPRINTED AT OXFORD <hi>by</hi> Ioſeph Barnes, <hi>and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yeard, at the ſigne of the Tygres head,</hi> 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:2"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend, Vigilant and Learned father in <hi>God,</hi> Thomas Cooper
<hi>the Biſhop of Wincheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>OEMES, RIMES,</hi> and Verſes, ſome of them haue their delight, ſuch as it is being ſung to the Lute, or Harpe, and weltuned inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but beeing read &amp; duly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered proue litle worth: with the Songs in ſcripture, and Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> it is neuer ſo. If wee ſing them they affect the conſcience, and when wee reade them they inſtruct the ſoule, as the other partes of the Bible.</p>
            <p>To theſe two endes, I haue dealte in a verſe out of the Kingly Prophet, amongſt your Lordſhips countrimen and mine, the Cittizens of <hi>Oxforde.</hi> I knowe you wiſhe them well in Chriſt Ieſu with a ſpeciall affection, and for my ſelfe, I haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent experience of your good loue to mee ward. The conſiderations whereof haue mooued me the rather to make bold, to
<pb facs="tcp:1317:3"/>deliuer forth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in writing this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnder your L. name right wel repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of &amp; deſeruedly in this place, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that his late moſt falſe, ſhameles, &amp; vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libelling wherof (I doubt not no kind of <hi>Sanardrin</hi> wil allow,<note place="margin">Martine Marpr.</note> &amp; which I am aſſured, the beſt &amp; beſt learned in the vniuerſity, in no degree do affect, but gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly lament, to ſee ſuch inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of tongs, and ſcorching fierbrandes to entermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, at the altar of the lord in his holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Were all thinges amiſſe, is this the way to reforme, by lying, libelling and comparatiue reproches?</p>
            <p>Nay, it may be if <hi>al his condicions</hi> were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto, yet conſidering his immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat behauiour immediatly enſuing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, it may be thought ſuch natures would neuer be quiet. So hard a matter it is (as the prouerbe is) to make a bed for a dog: for he wil alwaies haue it of his own making and faſſion. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious men wil contend and will neuer be contented.</p>
            <p>The corruptions of Patrons, the inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Miniſters, their requiſite diligence and ſome like matters of importaunce to be looked into and prouided for, by ſtrength of beſt authority, for mine owne
<pb facs="tcp:1317:3"/>part I doo greatly deſire. But this <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> humor hath, I know not what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vagarant and hungrie conceites. I craue pardon in reſpecting this man as he came in my way, I haue ſtept a ſide.</p>
            <p>Truly a Prophet commonly is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted where he is born and brought vp, &amp; for that cauſe Origen ſaith (but whence he had it I doo not know) that <hi>Paule</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preached at
<hi>Tharſis.</hi> But <hi>Oxford</hi> in this reſpect is no <hi>Tharſis,</hi> &amp; you ioy to heare of their ſome more towardnes then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>At the vttering this matter, me thought God mooued their harts, and I ſawe it in their faces. Yet becauſe that warmth or heate taken at the fire within, may bee ſoone cooled abroad in the winde I haue yeelded to the ordinary meane, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that external cauſe of their warmth to the preſſe, whereby they may ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as it were in their bozom a fier about with them: Firſt as a ſignification or effect of my harts deſire to doo them this good at this time principally, and then alſo as an intimation of a greater dutye to your Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>Some yeres ſence I conferred Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:1317:4"/>who was Dauids ſonne, his eſtate with Queene Elizabeths raigne before the Vniuerſity, and they haue it printed and reprinted, becauſe ſome very fewe at their pleaſure, muſt needes haue it ſo.</p>
            <p>Here before the towne I haue aſſaied with like breuity to doo the like, in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salomons fathers comforts towarde vs and our Qeene, praying God from my very hart that his bleſſinges toward fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſonne, to Dauid and vnto Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, may intirely and ioyntly be and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue moſt longe with her, and with her realmes to the worldes end, and namely in our proportion with vs, both Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Towne, and generally ſo withall the whole Iſraell of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From New Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 7. 1588.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALME. 23. ver. 4.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Though I ſhould walke through the valley of the ſhadowe of death, I wyll feare no euill: for thou art with mee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He caſe with <hi>Dauid</hi> at this time was not ſo hard, as to walke in the valley of the ſhadowe of death. For the Lord was his ſheephearde in open ſight, and ledde him as a ſhepe of greateſt care into his paſtures, and they greene and ſweet for foode, ſoft and eaſie for reſt, Situated by the waters ſide for beſt refreſhing in hotter countries.</p>
            <p>Onely in this verſe he may ſeeme to put the caſe, and conſidering the goodneſſe of God ſundry times to him-warde experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, he ſolemnely proteſteth vpon the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, fal out what may, and though he walke and often conuerſe in the vallie of the ſhade of death, that is, in the middes of moſt gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and horrible daungers, hee would not feare, for his hope was with God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Forecaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what may come</note>By the way I note: that <hi>Dauid</hi> amideſt his greene paſtures, where hee wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and in his greateſt eaſe, and higheſt excellencie, recordeth the vallie of miſerie,
<pb facs="tcp:1317:5"/>and ſhade of death which might enſue, if God ſo would, and therewithall reckoneth of his ſafeſt harbour, and firme repoſe, euen in God alone.</p>
            <p>And this is true wiſedome indeede, in fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e weather to prouide for a tempeſt, in health to thinke of ſickneſſe, in proſperitye, peace and quietneſſe, to forecaſt the worſt, and with the wiſe Emite in ſommer to lay vp for the winter following.</p>
            <p>The ſtate of man is full of trouble, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the godly man more. Sinners muſt be corrected,<note place="margin">The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this life.</note> and ſonnes chaſtiſed, there is no queſtion. The Arke was framed for the waters, the Ship for the Sea, &amp; happy is the marriner that knoweth wher to caſt Anker. But O bleſſed is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that can take a right Sanctuary, and knoweth wherupon to rely and in whom to truſt in the day of his neede. <hi>I wil not feare: for thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſheepe is a ſimple thing to deuiſe eſcape, impotent and vnarmed, and fearefull by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore vnable to reſiſt daunger, wherevnto notwithſtanding <hi>Dauid</hi> reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him ſelfe, voucheth boldly he will not fear, the Lord being with him.</p>
            <p>In the whole I obſerue, and ſhall moſt beate vpon theſe three thinges. Firſt, the
<pb facs="tcp:1317:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>gate and conuerſation, the walk of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vppon <hi>Dauids</hi> ſuppoſall. <hi>Though I walke.</hi> Then, his comfort he conceiueth in all his waies, <hi>I will not feare.</hi> And thirdly the grounde of his confidence to bee in the preſence of God,
<hi>For thou art with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tennor of <hi>Dauids</hi> life, and the waies he walked are manifeſt in the comperts and euidences of the Bible.</p>
            <p>In his nonage he was the leaſt, and of leaſt account in the familie of <hi>Iſai,</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his father, not called to the feaſt, and in the campe diſpitefully reproched of his eldeſt brethren, afterward <hi>Saul</hi> enuieth, <hi>Shimy</hi> raileth, <hi>Abſalon</hi> rebelleth, <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phell</hi> conſpireth, &amp;c. Theſe were vallies of vehement diſtreſſes, briefelye theſe with diuers others as you may reade, collected and quoted,<note place="margin">By D. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldes 1586.</note> &amp; I pray you doe in a Sermon of thanks giuing at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apprehenſion of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, to wit, <hi>Ballard</hi> and <hi>Babington,</hi> and their complices.</p>
            <p>But you wil ſay, how ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> he wold not feare: did he not flye &amp; diſſemble who he was? Or if he fled, as no doubt he did, from the ſpeare of <hi>Saule,</hi> was it not for feare?</p>
            <p>Feare is a quality incident to all fleſh: &amp; in this, &amp; the like naturall affections,<note place="margin">Feare.</note> a fixed
<pb facs="tcp:1317:6"/>mind, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant mene, is hardly obtaned. What <hi>Dauid</hi> did is not denied, &amp; it is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> as elſe when, ſo namely he greatly fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 20.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he fled to <hi>Achis,</hi> his &amp; gods enemy, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid in a ſhiuering perplexity: <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, ther is ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a ſtrid betwixt me &amp; death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Pſalme, I take it is rather vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not what the Prophet alwaies perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but what in duety muſt be performed, and what <hi>Dauids</hi> purpoſe was to endeuour vnto for the time to come. For after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pledges of Gods infinite goodnes vnder the guidaunce of his rodde, and ſtay of his ſhepe-hooke, godwilling he would not feare and this is the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d-worke of his affiance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> in the goſpell by our Sauiour in conſideration of infirmity thorough feare denying his maiſter,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> is willed after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion by that fauorable aſpect of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to confirme his brethren, &amp; to traine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in conſtancy: for verely god requireth ſetled minds, reſolute men &amp; confirmed brethren.</p>
            <p>So vpon occaſions paſt, <hi>Dauid</hi> found it true that he ſhould not haue bene heretofore at any time, and therfore profeſſeth, that, for the time to come, he would be no Marigold-ſeruaunt of God, to open with the Sun and ſhut with the dewe, to ſerue him in calmer

<pb facs="tcp:1317:6"/>times only, and at a neede to ſhute neck out of coller, fearefully and faithleſly to ſlippe a ſide, or ſhrinke away.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Newters reproued.</note>(Good people) in all hartleſſe imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, marke I pray you, that they, who feare euery miſt, that ariſeth, or cloude that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, who are like the Mulberie tree, that neuer ſhuteth foorth, or ſheweth it ſelfe till all hard weather be paſt, who like ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by and lookers on, Neuters, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimiſters, who like
<hi>Metuis Suffetius</hi> dare not venture vpon, nor enter into, nor inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour any good action of greateſt duetie to God, Prince or Countrie, till all be ſure in one ſide, are vtterly reprooued by this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample.</p>
            <p>If the cauſe bee Gods, if the quarrell bee neceſſary, if thy calling ſuteable, if it bee a croſſe that God layeth vpon thee in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith and trueth, and requiſite offices appertayning to pietie and charity, though it be a vale of daungers, Loe, <hi>Dauid</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he cannot, he will not yeelde, he will not feare, much leſſe diſpaire, and houer a loofe, or let all alone as men amazed and aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in their feminine affections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter,</hi> of whom before, hearing that the ſheepeheard ſhould be ſmitten,<note place="margin">Peter.</note> and the ſhepe
<pb facs="tcp:1317:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſcattered into ſundry vallies of imminent daunger, notwithſtanding boſteth himſelfe that he forſooth, hee would not forſake his maiſter, and though the reſt flie, hee alone would endure the combate, and not relente at all.</p>
            <p>The ſheepheard is ſmitten, and the flocke indeede is ſcattered, the reſt flye,
<hi>Peter</hi> more then flyeth,<note place="margin">Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth little.</note> for he denieth; and more then feareth, for he, of all the reſt, forſweareth his maiſter. And ſo it fareth euer, when men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paringly ſet out themſelues as Giantes, in theyr own conceites, though it be in cauſes of beſt account. Yet in the ende they come ſhorte of theyr reckoning. But <hi>Dauid</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon a ſurer rocke, then on himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In ſo many his exceeding daungers, hee will not feare. Why? the Lord is his ſheep-heard, no Idoll, or abſent ſheepehearde, but ready to helpe: and able to ſuccour.</p>
            <p>In the boke of <hi>Geneſis</hi> this was <hi>Iacobs</hi> comfort continually in all his viages,<note place="margin">Iacob.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Canaan</hi> into <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> or from <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> to and fro ſtill, <hi>Loe, the Lord was with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſix and fortith Chapter, he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to repaire into <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to feare, and the reaſon was, God
<pb facs="tcp:1317:7"/>himſelfe would goe downe with him, and conduct him thither, &amp; preſerue him there.</p>
            <p>And for that as children, which ride on reedes, are ſoone ouertaken in their folly, ſo olde men may become children againe, and reſt ouer much in ordinary hopes liable to ſenſe, and probable in reaſon. God willeth <hi>Iacob</hi> in effect, to forſake ſuch vaine cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, for cheefe releefe in the vſage, as of his own experienced yeres, his ſons place &amp; fauour with the prince, &amp; the like, and only commandeth: <hi>Fear not <hi>Iacob,</hi> I wilbe with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good cauſe, and why ſhould <hi>Iacob,</hi> or <hi>Ioſua</hi> in the firſt of
<hi>Ioſua,</hi> or <hi>Gedeon</hi> in the ſixt of <hi>Iudges,</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> before theſe, the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>Exodus,</hi> or any of vs all after them feare, if God be with vs, as he wil be,<note place="margin">Matth. 28</note> 
               <hi>With his to the end of the world?</hi> If God be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs who can be againſt vs, effectually againſt vs to our finall deſtruction?</p>
            <p>If God be with vs, what can we want? he that walketh in the ſun, doth he lack light? He who walketh with God by his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, as <hi>Enoc</hi> did, and with whom God walketh by his ſpeciall grace (for there is a ſpeciall reſpecte betwixte the grace of God and a gratious life) what is there, or
<pb facs="tcp:1317:8"/>what can there be wanting? By the grace of God we are that we are, and his grace in his is not in vain. In his light we ſee light, &amp; in his ſtrength we are more than conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ghoſtly euer &amp; euer bodily if it bee for the good of the ſufferer, and for the glorie of god, for whoſe cauſe, and in whoſe preſence, and by whoſe wiſedome we ſuffer, and hold out.<note place="margin">Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence is known but vnto gods own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The true meditation whereof (deer bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) to the careleſſe &amp; godles man, is as a riddle, or a claſped booke, or ſealed letters, which are brought by the carier &amp; ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled of many, but are read of none, nor vnderſtoode of anie, ſaue of him that of him that openeth them, and conceaueth the purport of them, and meaning of the ſender.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob</hi> (the holy man) in his loſſe of goods,<note place="margin">Iob.</note> death of children, perſonall extremities, wiues curſed motions, and to thoſe vnwiſe inferences and concluſions of his friendes replyeth, at one time: <hi>Naked I came into the world,</hi> at another time, <hi>The Lord gaue and the Lord hath taken away,</hi> at another to his Wife,
<hi>ô foliſh woman:</hi> &amp; to his frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, <hi>ô ye Phyſicions of no valu.</hi> But euer reſolutly that euen in death he knew that he hadde a liuing redeemer, and ſo thorough
<pb facs="tcp:1317:8"/>faith controuling his ſome impatiencie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizeth, that God the redeemer of al his, was alſo in ſpeciall his redeemer, and that it was not with God, as it may bee with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſtanding on the ſhore, may ſe a far-of theyr deereſt freendes and fellowe parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners plunged in daunger, and cannot helpe them, nor dare come to them.</p>
            <p>When I recount the great deliuerances of olde, in fiers, in waters, in miery caues, &amp; dreadfull priſons, of <hi>Elias</hi> vnder the Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tre, <hi>Moſes</hi> in the flagges, the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the furnace, and of <hi>Ionas</hi> in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of the Fiſh, in the bottome of the ſea, and altogether intangled, as it were, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rootes of the depth, who was with him, or with the reſt? or if God had not beene with them, in what caſe had they beene?</p>
            <p>Theſe were men as we are, and as ſaint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of one of them,<note place="margin">I am. 5, 17.</note> ſubiect to the like paſſions: The onely difference is, they were more excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their daies, and famous in theyr times, and therfore the rather regiſtered as moſt fitte examples of comfort to al poſterity for the time to come.</p>
            <p>More generall are the enſamples of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi> in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and of
<hi>Iudah</hi> in <hi>Babilon,</hi> both which people God in his good time, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring
<pb facs="tcp:1317:9"/>his mercy, and pittying theyr miſery, did wonderfully deliuer.</p>
            <p>But there is no difference with God, to be with one or with many, to deliuer ſome fewe, or greater companies. All is one with the almighty. Some difference only may be this, which is in books printed of a large or a leſſe letter, and paper, the matter not varying at all.</p>
            <p>When God tooke his people from the fierie furnace, and mierie clay, and from the vnceſſaunt toile of gathering ſtrawe, when he brought all <hi>Iſraell</hi> out of bondage, and left not an
<hi>hoof</hi> behind, here the preſence of God is printed as it were in Royall paper and in Capital letters. Againe, when <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> wordes,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Deus prouidebit,</hi> when, I ſay, Gods prouidence is ſeene priuately, and felt priuately of ſome one, the foorm and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per are leſſe, and the letter leſſe, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God is the ſame, And yet the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage may bee ſuch that it may be more to doo for one, then for many, and I conſter <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe to be of this kinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> kept his fathers ſheepe,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note> and there came a Lion, and likewiſe a Beare, and tooke a ſheepe out of the flocke. But <hi>Dauid</hi> (far vnlike ſome hirelings) followeth after,
<pb facs="tcp:1317:9"/>ventereth his life, redeemeth his ſheepe, and ſlaieth the Beaſt. This had beene ouerhard for <hi>Dauid</hi> to haue done, had not God beene with him. For he was but a youth.</p>
            <p>Farder, when he came to the campe, and heard the vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed Gia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t braue the hoaſt of the liuing God, ſtraight way in a mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machie, that is to ſay, one to one, himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with the Giant alone entred the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat, and according to <hi>Sauls</hi> wiſh at that tyme, <hi>The Lord was with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proceſſe, when <hi>Saule</hi> ſlue his thouſand, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſlue his ten thouſand, euery Damſell could ſing of the oddes, euen to the regreete of <hi>Saule,</hi> that ſought enuiouſly therefore to be diſpatcht of <hi>Dauid.</hi> But <hi>Dauid</hi> euer delt wiſely in all his waies, for why, <hi>The Lord was with him,</hi> ſayth the text.</p>
            <p>Now yet if <hi>Dauid</hi> for euer after ſhould haue leade onely a priuate life, the caſe had beene leſſe to ſee to then it was afterwards vpon great euents enſuing. For God had a purpoſe to take him from the ſheepfoldes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> &amp; to place him in roome of his maiſter to feed his people and guide his inheritance, ſo that al along Gods, being with <hi>Dauid,</hi> was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by him to be with his people, and with his inheritaunce.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Princes good or bad are the good or the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie bane of their ſubiectes.</note>For if God reſpect the Prince that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently is, or apparantly &amp; conſequentlie ſhal be, it is the benefit of many: for the Prince is as the ſtomacke in the body of a realme, it receiueth little for it ſelfe, but moſt for the reſt parts of the body. All ſence is from the head, all life is from the hart. The Prince is as the head and hart of his people and for the excellencye of his various properties, hath diuers reſemblances.</p>
            <p>If the root be quicke the branches grow: if the foundacion be ſure, all the building is the ſurer. A ſcholerly recitall with applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herein is ouer eaſie.</p>
            <p>And againe if the foundation be as a tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering wall, or rotten hedge, or ſlippery ſoile and quick ſandy, the building cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>Like Prince,<note place="margin">1. King. 14.</note> like people for the moſt part as it is written, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> was not a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alone, but he made all Iſraell to ſinne. And againe, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> fel away from God (like a great Oke) and Iſraell (ſome as greater armes, ſome as leſſer braunches) but all fell with him.</p>
            <p>And contrariwiſe againe in times of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regiment, it went better. Iſraell ſerued the Lord all the dayes of <hi>Ioſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſu. 24.</note> and all the like elders that ouer liued <hi>Ioſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:10"/>
            <p>Looke to it ye rulers, but you are not the cheefe rulers, if ſkilleth not, you are rulers, leſſe or more authoritie in rulers, dooth not alter the nature of ruling in your degrees. And water may be pure in the ſpring, &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in the riuers, if it bee not looked to.</p>
            <p>But God being both with the ſpring, and with the riuers, ſee, how is the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d refreſhed as in <hi>Dauids</hi> time and in <hi>Salomons</hi> time? And to theſe happy endes was God with
<hi>Dauid,</hi> as with a ſhepe of his own paſtures and with the worke-manſhip of his owne framing, to moſt ſoueraigne purpoſes, as you haue heard.</p>
            <p>AND now to looke homeward a little reflexiuely ſomewhat conſidering our own eſtate,<note place="margin">Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> euen by this glaſſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, you remember, I am ſure, who ſhe is that ſaid, <hi>Tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ouis,</hi> that ſhe was a ſhepe, euen in the vallie of death, leade vnto, &amp; ſhut vp in the ſlaughter houſe, and you may not forget, who he is that tooke the knife out of the butchers hand.</p>
            <p>You knowe who ſhe is that built vppon the rocke, and you know who that rocke is. Who hath not hard of that morneful voice, that <hi>She had no freend,</hi> &amp; yet comfortable in this,
<hi>But God alone:</hi> for how is he frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,
<pb facs="tcp:1317:11"/>that hath god for his frind? his word is a good, &amp; a true word. <hi>Win-God, and win al.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One ſayd, he was neuer leſſe alone, then when he was left alone, I ſay it is true, in ſence that when al men forſake vs, and God alone tarieth with vs, then are wee neuer leſſe alone.</p>
            <p>Good Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> hath founde it ſo, and God mollified the harts of ſome of her foes for his mercy ſake at her praiers, &amp; raiſed vp ſome others, dutifully and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to demeane the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnto her grace, and one ready to die at her foote, if vilanous bouldnes ſhould cauſe ſuch neede, and after ſome long ſeaſoning of ſo precious a woode for an excellent building, the happy <hi>17.</hi> day of <hi>Nouember, 1558.</hi> commeth, and God maketh it manifeſt to all the worlde, that himſelfe was with her in all theſe tempeſts, and then the plat-forme was broken vp, and the ſnare taken away, and a daughter of <hi>Dauid</hi> had as great deliueraunces as euer <hi>Dauid</hi> had, and ſo her owne confeſſion both then an ſince is a duefull and true confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That neuer Prince, no neuer creature had euer greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet becauſe this world is not the land of entire bleſſednes, euerlaſtingly to endure,
<pb facs="tcp:1317:11"/>ſundry vncleane beaſts haue entered, with ful entendment to ſtaine the greene and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paſtures wherein God hath placed her, and had done ſo (ſo it might haue beene) if God and his Chriſt, the great ſheepehearde of our ſoules had not exerted his arme, and ſhewed himſelfe, and ſtoode in the gap, and driuen away the Lion and the Beare, and the Popes ſundry Bulles.</p>
            <p>Verily as <hi>Elias</hi> his ſeruaunt ſawe a ſmall cloud by little and litle growing to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matter: ſo (good countrimen) the cheefe ſeruauntes of God in the honorable ſeruice of the realme and her Maieſty by that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency which God hath lent them, haue a long time ſince, looking for ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as the wicked world offereth eſpied the riſing and proceedinge of a cloude to come, ſometimes thickning in the North, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times threatning in the Weſt, and of late time, all the waters of the ſalt Ocean, and briniſh natures aſcendinge and leaguinge themſelues together to haue ouerwhelmed vs all, but the ground and ſubiect of theyr practiſes and complots failing them, and that onely or cheefe Pole-ſtarre of theſe home-conſpiracies and forraine drifts and troubles euen againſt her own onely ſonne,
<pb facs="tcp:1317:12"/>being taken away, they haue miſſed theyr aime, <hi>Her will and teſtament,</hi> mencined in her letters to <hi>Mendoza to giue away the realme, to the King of Spaine,</hi> could not be prooued, nor that <hi>Tragical execution</hi> be executed &amp; performed. And all theſe waues breaking in the fale, haue ſwallowed vp ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, who would haue deuoured vs: &amp; by the prouidence of him that keepeth <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> the ſtrong horſe &amp; the proud rider, thoſe tale ſhips, and furniture in them lie floting in the waters, and ſincke in the ſea. for ſince we deſiſted to chaſe and perſue them moſt of this is come to paſſe, to the ende cheeflie to ſhewe and declare that this was not the worke of man, but the hand of God.</p>
            <p>At theyr comming wee had warning of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at their entry we had a good beginning in their paſſage we gained the winde, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God gaue it vs, &amp; when they were roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ouer-right vs, they were diſplanted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. In theſe things, &amp; in whatſoeuer elſe either going before, or paſſed ſince, hee that ſeeth not the finger of God to haue bene, and to be with Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſeeth nothing and the brightnes of God ſhining vpon her, and by her vpon vs, dooth dazell his ſight, that he cannot ſee.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:12"/>
            <p>Wherin, the care of her maieſty, the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy of her honorable councel, the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of nobles, courage in Captains &amp; ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, with ioynt willingnes of all Engliſhe harts in the realme, were merueilous vaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp; commendable, but except God keepe al in order &amp; except he had vnited vs in true wiſedome to forſee and in harty rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntance to fly vnto him, &amp; in his ſtrength boldly and happily to withſtand theſe titulary conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, their pride might haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more fooliſh and moſt wicked to venter vppon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens dominions without end. <hi>Plus vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, More, <hi>ſtil More, was his fathers poſie.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Charls the. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But bee it that they haue receiued no harme by our reſiſtaunce, as their louers faine, bee it that our weapons haue ſtunge them like <hi>Plinies</hi> flies, and that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they doo not feele what we haue don by <hi>Our peccatores, by our little poor ſinners,</hi> For ſo at firſt they could terme our Nauy &amp; imagine of our ſhips, bee it that God by vs was not againſt them, yet certainely, they cannot deny and wee muſt confeſſe to the worlds end, that <hi>The Lord was with vs,</hi> &amp; herein we reioice &amp; praiſe his name for euer more, &amp; the more we giue to God, it is moſt true, that the great benefit of the ſea about
<pb facs="tcp:1317:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in our Queene, her Councel, nobles, &amp; peoples: abrod her Admiral, Viſeadmirals and ſkilful Sea-men: or any where elſe, her forces, poliſies, and helpes whatſoeuer, ſhal haue neuer a whit the leſſe, as the widdowe had neuer the leſſe,<note place="margin">1. King. 17</note> the more ſhee gaue to Gods Prophet.</p>
            <p>Wherfore (my good brethren and deere countrimen) lift vp your harts, lift them vp vnto the Lord and praiſe his holy name. He that offereth praiſe, honoureth him with an acceptable ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>Conſider then all his benefites, his olde, late, and his preſent benefites euen heaped vpon our Queene, and vpon vs her ſubiects and lay them all as diuers ſweetes togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make a Leuits fier of perfit thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes that ſhall neuer out.</p>
            <p>When a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Prince and an <hi>Italian</hi> Prieſt ruled England, when ſuperſtition, humane deuiſes, will-worſhippinges, and groſſe idolatrie in a ſtrange toung ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led al, then were our goods ſpoiled, our fleſh martyred, our bodies burnt, and our aſhes ſcattered, and our very ſoules ſterued.</p>
            <p>A ſlight remembraunce of this good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie from theſe calamities is little worth and as fier of bruſh ſoone extinct, lay alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather
<pb facs="tcp:1317:13"/>which hath followed ſince, conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies detected, rebellions repreſſed and preuented, inuaſions diuerted euer by the Lords owne doing, &amp; ſtil bleſſing
<hi>embrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, infolded,</hi> &amp; powred down bleſſing vpon bleſſing with a full horne? Truely the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunces of <hi>Dauid</hi> were but a caſt of thoſe which we feede on.</p>
            <p>Papiſts, the peeuiſhe and worſt ſorte of them bite the lippe hereat, and hang downe head not knowing, God knoweth, that their heads ſhould be hanged vp ſooneſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the heades of the richeſt, for <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> and <hi>Caluineſts,</hi> as well as other. Alas Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. Allen.</note> who euer ſtandeth aloofe as
<hi>Pirrhus poſt principia,</hi> cannot be alwaies at hand with euery barberous ſouldier, to ſay, <hi>This man forſooth is a Catholique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, for this time hether to (God bee thanked) <hi>Iacobs</hi> hand hath beene ſtronge enough to hold <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heel, and if ſome Midwiues helpe out blooddy <hi>Eſaus</hi> forces once againe, God that hath preſerued vs ſo long, will not, we hope, forſake vs now.</p>
            <p>Yet ſweete wordes lull men a ſleepe, the beſt <hi>Remora</hi> and ſtay to keepe them of, is an vnfayned repentaunce, and a generall conuerſion, and certaine determination of
<pb facs="tcp:1317:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the whole la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſerue him better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, &amp; in all theſe victories, or happie ſucceſſes to preſcribe al to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cheefe directer.</p>
            <p>The Flye in the Beaſts eare, or the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite on his horne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſay they were they who plowed the land, and brought, aboute theſe matters.</p>
            <p>If we haue done great thinges, hee hath don them by vs, &amp; as one ſaid to his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, if I be an Egle, you be my feathers: ſo if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Captaines or Souldiers haue done any thing, the Lord of hoaſts hath beene with vs all in al. And as he is a fooliſh Inne-keeper that keepeth not a perfect remembraunce of his cheefeſt geaſtes by whom he gaineth: ſo vnwyſe are we, if we forget by whom we haue profited, and by whome wee haue ſo greatly and ſo often gained,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leah</hi> beareth one ſonne, and calleth hys name <hi>Reuben,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen.
29.</note> a ſecond ſonne, and calleth him <hi>Simeon,</hi> and a third, and calleth hym
<hi>Leui.</hi> But when aboue expectation ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, and bareth the fourth time, ſhe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely calleth his name, <hi>Iudah,</hi> and expreſly proteſteth that <hi>She will praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If one benefit moue thee not, O England, many ſhould, if many haue not done it, yet this late deliueraunce paſſeth all others, O
<pb facs="tcp:1317:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>call it <hi>Iudah,</hi> and let vs prayſe the Lord. For any comfort ſaue in the Lorde, is like Agars water, that is ſoone dryed vp: but that ſweete acclamation in the Prophet <hi>Zacherie, Grace, Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4.</note> is the euerlaſting duetie of our Churche and common weale and the fatneſſe of his Oliues, and the conſolations of his ſpirite, and his beeing with our Candle-ſtick is our onlie comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary news in Spaine. 1569.</note>Others imagine fabulous tales, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hopes: feare them not: About the yeere of our Lord <hi>1569.</hi> or ſome-what after, I reade, of falſe newes ſpread in Spaine of a ſuppoſed great battaile betwixte the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Chriſtians, wherein an Angell with a Challice in his hand, was reported to haue diſcomfited manie thouſands of our Queenes ſubiectes for the which putatiue victorie, there were in Spaine gratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and triumphes in the bieſt degree with concourſe of nobles, ringings and ſingings, and much mad mirth, for the fortunate ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe againſt the heretiques according to the meaning of the Pope-holy league, and charitable conſpiracy of the couent of
<hi>Trent.</hi> Belike ſome <hi>Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doza</hi> ſent theſe news, they were ſo true. Sence the Spaniards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue had a long thirſt to drink of the
<pb facs="tcp:1317:15"/>ſame cup, and out of the Challice which the Angell held then forth. And this fatall yere <hi>88,</hi> they haue ſought for it in England, and they haue taſted thereof in Ireland, wee know, and I think al Spaine would ring if not therefore, yet thereof by this time, if the king, or rather, if the holy houſe would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them.</p>
            <p>A little thing would make fooles fayne now, they were ſo a gogge at nothing then. But proud
<hi>Bennadab,</hi> muſt not boſt, when he girdeth his harneſſe, as when he putteth it of. But O fooliſh fugitiues and Engliſhe Seminaries, &amp; ſeedemen of theſe tumults, what meane you, why ſeeke yee amity with euery ſtraunger? Euen therefore God hath demonſtratiuely taught you that your tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries are wicked. Why goe you abroade? what want you at home? Becauſe our Queene truſteth in the Lord &amp; in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the moſt high, ſhe and we haue not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caried, and God hath beene with vs, and though we be not as we ſhould be, yet, good God, make vs better. They are thine open enimies. To make an ende for this time tyl on Tueſday next, when (God willing) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to our bounden duetie we meete againe, and then we ſhall ring for them, and
<pb facs="tcp:1317:15"/>ſing for our ſelues and profeſſe in a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine veritie, that not an Angell, but God himſelfe had a fauourable eye towarde vs, &amp; an holy hand ouer vs, and that hee was as much with vs as euer with any Nation, when notwithſtanding all their crakes and famous
<hi>Dons,</hi> and doutie <hi>Aduenteres,</hi> huge ſhippes all to be-ſwathed with gables and printed vauntes, we loſt by them, who are now ſent home a wrong way, neither man, nor ſhip, nor boat, nor maſt of ſhip. <hi>O Grace, Grace. Thanckfulnes, Thankfulnes,</hi> call it
<hi>Iudah,</hi> and praiſe the Lord, the King of Kings, the God of armies and the Lord of hoſts, and mighty <hi>Iehoua</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:16"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. KINGS. 6.</bibl>
               <p n="15">15 <hi>Elizeus</hi> ſeruaunt ſeeing a great Hoaſt compaſſing the Cittie, Saieth to his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: <hi>Alas maiſter what ſhall we doo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16 The Prophet anſwereth. FEARE NOT: For <hi>they which be</hi> WITH VS <hi>(to witte God and his ſtrength) are moe then they which bee with them.</hi> And God opened the mans eies, who looked and ſawe that it was ſo.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:1317:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
